Guide to the Bush Family Papers 1824–1936 MS 3197
New-York Historical Society
Bush family papers
1824–1936
New-York Historical Society
Bush (Family)
MS 3197
0.63 Linear feet in 2 document boxes.
A small collection of deeds, address books, and financial items stemming from the Bronx-based Bush family, descendants of Scottish immigrant John S. Bush (1844–1913). Includes minutes of the John S. Bush Manufacturing Co., purveyors of ice, wood, and coal (1909–1919), and European travel diaries kept by Frances Maude (Morris) Bush (1928–1936).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carol Bush Richter (accession no. MS-2019-045), September 13, 2019.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in five chronological series:
Series I.
Real estate, 1824–1893
Series II.
Financial, 1874–1899, undated
Series III.
Address books, circa 1887–1891, undated
Series IV.
John S. Bush Manufacturing Co., 1909–1919
Series V.
Frances Maude (Morris) Bush travel diaries, 1928–1936
Biographical / Historical
Scottish immigrant John Stearns Bush (1844–1913) married Mary Jane Berrian (circa 1846–1920), a daughter of William Davis Berrian (1817–1903), in 1868. The couple had three known children—Marie Natalie (Bush) Balcom, John H. Bush, and William Berrian Bush—all of whom were officers or shareholders in the John S. Bush Manufacturing Co., the Bronx-based ice, coal, and wood business incorporated by the elder Bush in 1909. William Berrian Bush married in New York, in 1904, Frances Maude Morris (1871–1959).
[All names underlined are represented by documents in the present collection.]
Scope and Contents
The collection includes deeds, mortgages, and title abstracts for properties in The Bronx and in New Rochelle, Westchester County, New York, from the period 1824–1893; some financial fragments—a blank checkbook, some blank deposit slips, and a bankbook in the name of William D. Berrian in trust for the children of his daughter, Mary J. (Berrian) Bush—dating from 1874–1899; four address books, circa 1887–1891; minutes of the John S. Bush Manufacturing Co., purveyors of ice, wood, and coal, 1909–1919; and five travel diaries kept in 1928–1936 by Frances Maude (Morris) Bush of her ocean voyages to England, France, Italy, and other European countries.
Coal.; Ice -- Manufacturing processes; Wood.; Europe -- Description and travel -- 1919–1944; Real property -- New York (State) -- Bronx County.; Real property -- New York (State) -- Westchester County.; Address books.; Bankbooks.; Checkbooks.; Deeds.; Deposit slip.; Diaries.; Minutes (administrative records); Mortgages.; Title (property right); John S. Bush Manufacturing Co.; Bush (Family); Berrian, William Davis, 1817–1903; Bush, Frances Maude (Morris), 1871–1959; Bush, John Stearns, 1844–1913; Bush, Mary Jane (Berrian), approximately 1846–1920
- Series I. Real estate, 1824–1893
  - Deed. Elizabeth Clark Estate to James Secor, 1824 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Property at New Rochelle, Westchester County, New York.
  - Deed. Gouverneur Morris to Sebastian Jaclard, 1849 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Property at Morrisania, Bronx, New York.
  - Deed. William Weeks and w[ife] to Sebastian Jaclard, 1850 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Property at West Farms, Bronx, New York.
  - Mortgage. Francis C. Baptiste to John [G? I?] Horton, 1868 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Mortgage on property at New Rochelle, Westchester County, New York.
  - Deed. The Manhattan Savings Institution to John S. Bush, 1885 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Abstract of the Title of John S. Bush to three lots of land on Carter Avenue, 24th Ward, New York City, [1893] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Property on the west side of Carter Avenue near East 175th Street, Bronx, New York.
  - Abstract of the Title of John S. Bush to three lots of land on Carter Avenue, 24th Ward, New York City. Mortgaged to Francis B. Chedsey to secure payment of $3,000, [1893] (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II. Financial, 1874–1899, undated
  - Third Avenue Savings Bank. Account book (59850), William D. Berrian in trust for the children of Mary J. Bush, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    William Davis Berrian (1817–1903) was the maternal grandfather of the children of Mary Jane (Berrian) Bush (circa 1846–1920).
  - Bank of America, New York. Checkbook (blank), 1890–1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fifth Avenue Trust Co. Deposit slips (3), 1890–1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chase Manhattan Bank. Envelope with keys (3), [20th century] (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series III. Address books, circa 1887–1891, undated
  - Address books. "Pierce's Memorandum and Account Book" (3), circa 1887–1891 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Address book (1), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series IV. John S. Bush Manufacturing Co., 1909–1919
  - Minute book, 1909–1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes tipped-in stock certificates and tax returns.
  - Stock book, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Blank except for tab "B," recording the names and information of John S. Bush, William B. Bush, and John H. Bush.
- Series V. Frances Maude (Morris) Bush travel diaries, 1928–1936
  - Travel diary, 1928 September 12 – October 24 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Embossed "My Travels." Record of voyage aboard the RMS Aquitania and visits to England and Belgium.
  - Travel diary, [1928] October 25 – December 17 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Embossed "Mrs. William B. Bush." Record of visits to France, Italy, and Switzerland.
  - Travel diary, [1928] December 18 – [1929] August 16 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Record of visits to France and Germany.
  - Travel diary, 1930 June 3 – July 26 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Embossed "My Trip Abroad" and "Frances M. Bush." Record of visits to England, Scotland, and Baltic countries.
  - Travel diary, 1936 July 29 – September 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    A 1935 pocket calendar issued by Siefke & Rosenblum, General Insurance, 2 West 45th Street, New York, and used as a travel diary in 1936. Record of voyage aboard Queen Mary and visits to England and Wales.